you
am I audible?
yes, great, great, great
so let's begin
just quick show of hands in case my screen is visible
cool
cool then, let's begin
it is 9.05 I guess
we are all good, let's begin
so, hi I am Shashwath
I will be filling in for Uttam for
I think three classes
so in these three classes we will be talking
a lot about a lot of things
but we will also be talking about
some of the things that we will be talking about
so let's begin
so hi I am Shashwath
I will be filling in for Uttam for
but we will be getting started with
one of the most important things
especially when you think about front end development
so let me
so first of all
let us talk about the agenda for today
as you could see we have a couple of things on our board today
firstly I want to cover up what is in DOM
basically give you an idea what DOM is
then we will be talking about
how can we retrieve an element
because DOM is more like a tree structure
so how do we retrieve a particular element
out of that tree
and then we have to perform some operations on it
that would bring us to the third point
which is event and event listener
and certain functions
like createElement, appendChild, innerHTML, innerText
so I will be setting context
for all of these things
and we will try to cover all of these things
in today's class
cool
just a quick
reminder in case
you are not able to follow
feel free to raise your hand
feel free to comment
in the chat
I will be going over it
once again
all good
shall we begin
yes
yes yes yes
let us
begin
so I have
cloned the repository
that you guys were already working on
and I will be continuing
from that repo itself
cool
just give me a second
so let us get started
what is DOM
it is a very simple question
so let me write a bookish definition
for it first and then
we will understand it in detail
right
DOM basically stands for
document
object
model
that's it
that is what DOM is
now let me say
let me create
an index file here
I will fill in a couple of things
and here I will say
let me create a div here very simple
let me say
hello
scalar
and let me save this
and now I will
cool
so
I simply had written
I have simply
written here a very simple
HTML page which we will be
going through in detail
I have simply created here a single div element
and nothing else
you could go to the elements tab here
and here you could see everything
present here so this
matches exactly what I have written here
yes
can you increase the font in HTML
sure I can
cool
it should be
enough
so here
I have written hello
scalar here that is what it is reflecting here
so everything that you see here
is your DOM
and all of this is present on
your document
so let me say
document as you could see
the entire thing got selected
because inside of this document
I have the whole thing present
so this is why it is called
document object model
before I get into
detail what exactly DOM
is now so let me
write the definition for it
first and say
document
DOM is
DOM is a tree structure
in
which
every
HTML
element is
arranged in
a
hierarchical
order
so we have a couple of
keywords here
first is the tree structure
and second is arranged in
a hierarchical order
so we will be looking into
these two things why
did I say DOM is in a
tree structure and second why
one would
say the elements are arranged in a
hierarchical order
cool
so let's go to DOM
so here let me write
a very very simple
HTML document for you
here we could probably
have a div inside of this div
I could have let's say
two divs
in this particular div I could go on
to have an H2 tag I am sure
you are all aware of what H2 is
this is a H2 tag
and inside of this
div what I could have is
let's say H1
this is
a H1 tag
and I could
potentially have
a P tag as well
so now that
you look at this particular structure or
the whole thing as a whole
how do you visualize
it this is the way that
we are seeing it but there is a better way to visualize
it so let us look at that better
way of how we
can visualize it
so here
what we have is a document
sitting at the very top
as I mentioned at the very start and we saw
in the browser as well that
your whatever web page that you are seeing
all of it is inside
a document right so document
sits at the very top and
what is the first element that you all see here
what is the
first element that is visible
what is the first element which is visible at the
very top in here
other than doctype, doctype
simply tells you about what type
what type of a document it is
in our case it is HTML so
which is why it is written like this and if you see
there is no ending of doctype
it is just something that you are sort of like
announcing
correct, correct
so the top most element here is
HTML so let us put it
so let us put it like this so top most element
is HTML as you all pointed out which is
correct
so here I could say
I have
HTML correct
now what else
what is the next element that you
would see you would find here
inside of HTML what is there
correct yes
there is head
anything else other than head
correct
so head and body
it is not like they are on a different
level instead they are sort of like a sibling
so the parent element in
this particular case is HTML
that and inside of this we have
two elements one is head one
is body so let us make it like that
in
here we have head
and here we have
body
now if
I were to expand head likewise
now I am
say there is a meta
meta and there is a
title
likewise in body I have
a div
there is
inside of this div
I would be having two divs
which is two div siblings
and inside of one div
I have
H2 and inside of
another I have H1
and B
now one look at this
diagram and one look at this
does it like
does it look like a good visual
representation of your DOM
or of your HTML
yes or no
yes
and what data structure does this remind
you of
what does it look like to you
if you were to look at it upside down
won't it look like that
this particular part
so won't it look like
this particular part is sort of like
the trunk and here
goes all of the branches
which are further spreading out
at each direction
yes
so would it be fair to say
DOM
DOM is a tree structure
one look at it and would it be
right to say DOM is more or less
like a tree structure
yes
correct right
so because DOM is more or less like a tree structure
and if you look at it
one parent
can have as many
children as they want like in this particular
case HTML tile has two
children one is head
one is body in this particular case
head has three children
three children meta
meta title in this particular case
body has one further goes to have
two and then two and one
respectively right
which means a particular parent can have
multiple children but
no matter what element you pick
they will always
have only one parent
right so they form sort of
like a hierarchy yes or no
yes
yes I hope everyone is able
to follow so
now if you
look at it now
so DOM is a tree structure
in which every HTML element
is arranged in a hierarchical
order it makes sense now
right DOM is more or less
like a tree structure which
also maintains a hierarchical order
now since you are talking about
trees won't there be a root there
has to be a root element and
root element is sort of like the
top most element right
top most element of the tree and
the special thing
about root is that it does not have
a parent right
so in our case that
root element is
can you guess which one is a root
element do not include body
sorry document
so everything document has
a lot of things it encapsulates
the entire tree
so other than document what do you think
is a root element correct
so in our case
the root element is
HTML right
and
in simple terms
this is what document
object model is
now think of it like this no matter
what class you were to apply
no matter what HTML you were to write
all of it
will be eventually converted into
DOM and all of it
would eventually be reflected
in here right
and all of it would be eventually reflected
in here now there I think
you would be better able to see
HTML is at the top it has two children head
and body if you were to go down body
there is a div element further go
down there are two divs further
go down there is a H2 tag here in this day
there are two elements here so it is
sort of forming a tree
right and that is what
it is all about
and the
main part is
TV
we will be
using
JS
to put
interactivity
to
our
web apps
slash
websites
what does it exactly mean
when I say that I want to put
interactivity
what would be interactive
suppose if I were to hover over it or suppose
if I were to click on a button something happens
when I say something happens what do
I mean by that something changes suppose if
I were to click on this particular
suppose there was a button here for
example
click me
okay now
what would you say interactivity
is suppose if I were to click on this button
somehow this
thing were to change the
whatever is written here in this H1 tag
gets to change and let's say
it gets changed to
I am
the biggest
tag
out
here
would this qualify as
interactive website yes or no
if I were to click on this button click
me and it changed the
element the
whatever this particular H1 tag was written
to this would you say that this is interactive
yes because this
is interactive so what all things
if you were to break it down
all we did was
we changed the DOM
we went to the DOM and I simply
edited the thing
I edited the thing
here right so which
means it doesn't mean the interactivity
is nothing else but
changing DOM
elements or like accessing DOM
and you should be able to change certain
parts of it and that would qualify as
interactive yes or no
so far are we on the
right track does that
make sense
yes
great
cool
so
what I have in mind now
is I have prepared
a couple of questions here question
one two seven so we will try to
solve these questions in
today's class so obviously since we are
solving questions I will be needing help from your side
and while we are
at it in case you
I will be needing your suggestions and all
and we will try to solve as many
as possible
in today's class and
I will also give you a couple
as a homework
after the class cool
so does that sound good so
we will be learning things and then
we will be solving
questions and while we are solving them
we will also be learning the concepts
cool
so this is what the structure is going to be
for today's class
right
cool
so before
we move forward to the next topic
which is the first
question is this thing
clear to everyone
when I say that JavaScript will put interactivity
to your web apps all I am
saying is that using
JavaScript I should be able to access
certain DOM elements and
make changes to that DOM
element that's it
yes
so in that case
let's move on to the
very first question here
this is
Q1
so
okay this looks like a
friendly question it says say hello
but on click of it nothing is
happening let's see what the question is
question one on clicking of the button
append hello to the
page okay so
the idea is that I should be
able to append
certain thing
in here suppose
here you have a body right
I will say edit as HTML
and in here
I could have a p tag saying
hello
see hello's are getting
here
if I were to copy then
paste paste
so every time I click
this button I should be
adding a new
DOM element
p tag let's say for example and
in this I should be having
a hello right
so if I were to refresh because we were
doing it manually changing the DOM
we should be able to write
JavaScript to do this cool
so now
to solve this problem what do you think
should be the first thing that we should
do anyone
if I were to apply brute
force what was I doing first of all
I was able to
select my body
element and inside of this
body element I was
writing the p tag or any
tag for that matter and inside of that
tag I am writing hello
right so basically I should be having
this particular tag somewhat prepared
and I should somehow
know if someone has clicked
on this button only then I
should be adding that particular
element inside this body
correct does that sound like
a logical plan
yes Raja, Sambet,
Ashish, Tejal, Pradeep
correct
so
a couple of things
which are
important for us
to do that
we need to first somehow
identify an element
right how can I
possibly listen that
I am listening to this particular button
there could be n number of buttons present
on this page this is a very
simple example so which is why we don't have
any we only have one
button but since there could be
multiple buttons
yes Abhishek we are
gradually moving towards that only
I somehow need to identify
how can I
pinpoint on this button
and say that let me know
when someone clicks on this button
right so as
Abhishek and Tejal has pointed out one of the
way one of the many ways
that we could do so is using the
ID but how so
let us talk about that so before
we do I just like to mention that there
are a couple of ways we could
identify an element
methods
used to
identify
an
element
right
so one is
get
element
by ID
second is
query
selector
third is
query
selector
all
fourth is
get
element
by class
name
there are a couple more but
we will be focusing on
these four for now right so
let's start with a very very basic
one which is get element by
ID
so
since I mentioned all of the
elements all of all that you
are seeing on this particular web page is present
inside of one big object
can anyone help me remember what
that object was
document
right inside of this document
everything is there everything
that you see here is inside
of this document and one of the best things
about document is that all of these
methods are also
present inside of document
so how will I
be accessing get element by
ID I should be
able to write document
dot
get element by ID
so let's give it a try
let's say
document dot
get element now you see
a couple of options are popping up
here and I want to play
around with get element by ID
what do you think would be
the ID do we
have an ID on this particular button
yes or no
correct that is
btn so I will be putting
in double quotes here and say
btn and
it will be giving me the
reference to this button so which means I need to
store this reference with me somehow
so that I can use it at a later
point in time so let's say
I can say
cons
btn lm is equal
to this thing right
and now simply let me log
it btn
lm
and save this
oh
it's getting saved
let me add a comment as well
double button
element
cool it's showing up and as you could see as I'm hovering
over it it is basically highlighting
this but what if the ID was
somewhat different what if the ID
was let's say bt
nn
right
do you think would it be able to return
anything
no
correct so here now you could
see I'm getting null right
because no value was returned
so which means
when I'm saying get
element by ID I need to provide in
an element here
right and which is why
I need to do it like this
make sense
now if I go here the element is there
and now
suppose this
ID was not there instead a class
was there
can you help me
how can I access this
particular element now
there is no ID present here but a class
so how can I access it
correct
document dot
get element by class name
and what is the class name it is
btn so if I were to save
this
it is in here
cool
and
there is one more way
two more way actually
one is query selector and one is query
selector all this is going to be
interesting why so
let's say
query
selector
now do you think this
would work yes or no
let me change it back to ID
class name is also fine but
changing back to ID so now
do you think it would work
query selector basically says
tell me
what am I looking for and it will
traverse the dom
it will traverse this
particular dom in
search of that element
which matches the condition
in our case the condition is
document dot query
selector btn
do we have anything with btn in here
yes or no
yes but it would
still not be able to access it
why because
if you remember earlier we were using
we were using
get element by ID
or
get element by class name
so we were actually specifying
what exactly
is the attribute that I am looking
for be it ID
or be it class name but now
in query selector have I specified
is btn
is a class name or
an ID
have we specified it by any how
no right correct
we haven't so now if I were to
specify it that I am looking for
an ID called btn
how would you say so in CSS
how would you target
you must have
learned this in CSS selectors class
how would you target it
there is
a special symbol that was used
yes
it is
hashtag now that I put
in hashtag here if I were to save this
and go here yes the element
is targeted
and suppose if I were to change this to
class and save it
it would not be able to target it
because it is still looking for a btn
ID
if I were to say that btn is a class
in that case I need to put
dot in here and now
I am again able to
access it
so which means that
using these methods
I am able to access all of these
correct
so which means that
I am able to
pinpoint now what element
I am listening to
but
how do I say that
I am listening to this element
how do you say that
any idea
how would you say
I am able to access this but
how would I know whether the user
has clicked on it
so there is a very interesting thing
now which is very very important
in terms of
how we get
to it
think of it like
how does keyboard works
whenever I type in something
something must be telling the
cpu that okay
shashwat has typed this key
generator
shascaler
whatever I am typing
something is listening to every keystroke
and it is telling the cpu
that this person has typed this thing
so what do you think that is called
that is sort of like a signal
would everyone agree yes or no
so whenever I am typing something
somehow a signal is
sent inside and
what the cpu could be doing
cpu could be listening to that
signal correct
yes
abhimanyu abhishek ahmed ashi
shashwani
hemangi krishna pradeek
all able to follow right
let me know in case there are
any doubts
okay so there is
this signal happening my point
is ki is there a way
I could listen to those signals in my
case I am listening to
a click signal he whenever I am
clicking on this this particular button
I can somehow
attach a listener
right he that listens to a
particular signal there could be n number of
signals right like I could be double
clicking on it I could be clicking on it
I could be dragging it I could be doing a number
of things with this button but
the one event that
I am interested in is a
click button is a click
event basically click signal right
so in javascript that signal
is basically called event
what is an event whenever you do
any interaction
any interaction a event is
released
an event is released
and we are listening to that particular
event in our case the event that
we are listening to is on click
so let me open
w3
w3 school
events
now as you could see
these are some of the elements
on click on change
on mouse over on
this thing mouse out
like so there are
n number of such events present
right so what does it
say html events
are things that happen to
html element right in
our case what is happening to this particular
html element a click
right so let
us let me write down the definition
what exactly
is an event first
what is
event
anything
that happens
depending on
some
other thing
to an
html
element
is an
event right
so there is
a btl
someone
clicks on it
right in that case
a
click
event is
fired now
if a click event is fired I could
potentially listen to
that click element right and
I could know for a fact okay if this
particular event is fired which means
I need to do something
right so
let's go ahead and
write the code for
this now yes
good so
we already have the button element in
place and I want to attach
a particular listener
on this so what exactly
are we listening to
we are listening to a click event
correct
yes we are listening to a click event
event is the keyword here we are listening to a
click event so
what I am going to say here
you can read or you can read it
sort of like a English
statement also this particular line
that I am going to type
btlm
dot
add event listener
what event listener
I am listening to is click
right
and one of the best thing about JavaScript
is it will you can pass
a callback here a callback
is nothing but a function call
so you could say to you if
on this particular btlm element
you listen a click event
you have to execute
this
function
and this function you will be getting
a event
right that was fired
so let me just log
event
event fired
so now let's go in here
all clear
where I click on this hello
button say hello
see event fired and what
was the event pointer event
if I were to expand it see
so much information was shared
with us
now using this information
if we want we can play around with things
and you could see
it also has the element also
the target where the
element was fired for basically it's the
source
and it has the entire
thing about all the information
about this particular button that you could
possibly be needing right
and it is a very detailed
information that you could possibly use to
decide what you want to do now
right so now
I'm able to do two things using
only these four or five lines
of code I'm able to identify
in a huge
web application
I can somehow pinpoint
HTML element
and second thing that I'm able to do I'm able to
listen to a certain event
right suppose
we have a different event
event list in JavaScript
JavaScript
let's say there is
event list in
JS
suppose we have
mouse over
so I could probably listen to
and let's go back here
see I haven't
clicked on it as soon as my mouse is
hovering over it
it is launching an event
so likewise there are n number
of events but the event that we are interested
in is click event
and this particular event I'm getting
the event also that is being fired
cool now
all I have to do is
if you remember
the changes
that we were doing here I'm able
to
put an event listener to on this
particular element now
I'm able to know
that a particular event
is fired or basically someone
has clicked on this particular
button now what to do
what do we have to do let's revisit
the question or clicking of the button
so this part is sorted I'm able to
listen to it that now
the latter half is append hello
to the page
yes so let's go towards
this now so here
I will be creating an element
right let's say
let new
dev
lm is equal to
again for creation I'll be using
a function called create
element
this function it will basically
create an element and what element
I'm looking to create let's say
dev
I can choose to create any element
any
legit element that I want
I could create a p tag h1 tag
h2 tag span tag
or any possible tag
using this particular function now it
has basically created that element
and it is stored the reference in new
dev element and
what does the dev element
say hello
right so let me simply say
new dev
lm is equal to
hello right
now all that
is left is I somehow need to
put it on this term
inside our body right
so which we see again we have
to target body first
right so can anyone help me
targeting body
which of these
selectors we should be using
should we use get element by id query
selector query selector all
get element by class name I think
the most logical selector
that we could probably
use is query selector right
because there is
we can choose to put id or
class here but if you want
we can simply choose to use
query selector also right
so let me copy paste it
here and here I will say
body lm and here
I could simply say body
now this
new dev element that we have created
all I have to do now
I have the new element in place
and I have the
body lm
I know where the body element is
now all I have to do is
take this new dev element
and put it on the body
that's it right and how can we
do that
we can do that by saying
body
lm dot
append
so append is the function which is
used to append
something as in put something in it
and I will say new
dev lm that's it
now let us
quickly go through a dry run
of the logic
we have a btn element
document or query selector btn
I am targeting the btn element
I am putting an event listener
what event am I listening to click event
and I have given it a callback
so every time a click happens this particular
function will be called and in this
particular function what am I doing
I am creating a new dev element
and I am putting the value hello
on that new dev element and
then I am somehow getting
the target body
and I am appending this
new dev element that we have created
inside of
body element
is the logic sound
does it make sense
in an ideal world this should work
when I click on this it should
append something
let's see if it works
yes
it is
working
if I were to change this to
p tag then it will
do next
it's working
oh my god
I need to do
inner text
right
now
without manually
doing this
I am able to do this using
just javascript
yes
was it interesting
yes no
abhinav obanyu
ahmad ashwini
chandini dhangraj
hemant kishore krishna lapreet
uniswara kishore
krishna lapreet
uniswara pradeep rajakta pramod
raja rita charanya tanu
tejil shaykh
rohit shashank
vigneshwar
was everyone able to follow this part
why so many
hello because I clicked so many times
if I were to refresh all of
them would be gone if I click one time
then I am getting only one
right
now before we proceed to the
next question which is question two
any doubts
whatsoever
so far in whatever we have covered
any doubts anyone
yes no
inner text correct
so good point if you remember
what I had done previously
was I was able to
solve btn
let me
save this
we have the btn
element
when I click
I am getting the event
this is the target element
so this button for
any element
or any element as
these many key value pairs
as you could see re auto complete
null or almost everything
is null so one such element
which is present here must be
inner text this one
so basically this defines
what does this particular element
is going to say
so if I were to change this
it would basically reflect here so what I
had done here I was creating a new
p tag and inside of
that p tag I am simply setting this
inner text for that
p tag to hello
correct so likewise there are so many
properties that you could modify and play
around with so one such element
one such property that I played around with
was inner text
cool
cool upendra
ask come again once please
upendra
our strategy was simple
because we had to append hello on the page
on click I somehow targeted the button
using query selector
class because I had class here
so I added dot here I am
able to target that element
I was attaching event listener
to it what event click event
and I passed a callback function
in this callback function I am
simply saying that create a
new element p tag
to set the inner text value
of this newly created p tag
to hello and
post at
target the body element
and append this newly created
div element on that body
does that make sense
upendra code wise
code wise does that make sense
promote does that also
answer your question
yes
great great
cool
assuming it's all clear
to everyone let's quickly
take up question number two and question
number two is an interesting one because
in this question we will be learning about
a new way to select elements
that is query selector all
so let's do that
let's go through the question
here it says
fix the list by
inserting the missing element
using query selector all and
insert before
so far we have been
doing what we have been
appending now
we learn about two things
we learn about query selector all
and insert before
as the name suggest
we somehow have one
li tag missing here right
we have one two three four
five six
eight nine ten so seven
is missing so I need to somehow
target this eighth element maybe
and I can insert before
a li here
achha
so I am assuming ki
this part
would be easier right
I can
somehow
say
li
new li
lm
right
and in this all I have to say
is seven
so li I will make
here
the tricky bit
so this I can definitely make
using this way the tricky bit
is this how can
I make sure
ki it gets inserted
only at this place
not at the start not
at the end but
exactly as this place
right so this
is the challenge that we are trying to
solve here so let me
comment this for now because we will
come to that part so first we need to figure out
how will I get to this particular
element this particular space in between
so any idea anyone
anyone would like to take a rough guess
you don't have to be right but
you have to be active though
so as you could see
we have one two three four five six
seven is missing
then eight nine ten so seven
is something that we have to
integrate there so any
idea
okay
you will take a query selector
and target the parent
element okay that makes
sense so let's do that
so
what
let's say here we have net
ul is equal
to document dot
query selector
and here we are targeting
ul okay parent is now targeted
okay raja says query selector all
okay so basically
what i'll be getting is all of the list
items so let me say let
all list items
is equal to
document
dot query
selector all
okay
okay so now
what is the difference
in between
all list items
so what is the difference between query
selector and query selector all
what query selector does is that it will
target the first element
it will target the first element
which matches the condition and it will
call it a day
but not in the case of query selector all
it will keep on going and it
will return you a list
an array you could say
an array of all the elements
that basically passes this
condition this selection criteria
that you'll be
writing here right so in our
case all of this
these items would be returned so if I go
here you can see there are total and note
list of nine items one two three
four five six seven eight nine
but we have ten why because we have
one of the thing is missing here
and I can go here you can see
all those properties
are present here
so somewhere in here you see inner
text is visible which says six so
this thing this particular
li is for sixth
right likewise
we get to four three two
one and likewise
cool so now
so now the idea is
key now I am able to access
all of the list items I somehow
need to get access to the
eighth element
right and which index
is the eighth element in
it is in
sixth right
it is on sixth index yes or no
ah open the correct
it is on seven but array
starts from zero right
so on zero we have
one likewise it will keep
on going and eighth is on sixth
so which means
ah correct
so which means what
I can do here is
that to make things somewhat
easier I can say
const
e i g h eighth
l m is equal to
all list items
and the index was sixth
so now I am on sixth element
right so
I can
uncomment
this
now right
and let me say
seventh length
right
in this I can say
inner text is equal to seven
now all I have to do
is insert it before
this right but
how does insert before works
lets look at it
so how does insert before
works it takes
a li element create a text node
insert
so
insert basically
takes in two things
and
hmm
I need to
add a new node first
in our case the new node is
seventh element
and I also need to add
lay
what are we inserting it before
right in our case we are
inserting it before the eighth element
and all of this
needs to be done on a list so which means
a parent would also
be needed does it work on click
no it won't work
on click up you know
as soon as your javascript gets loaded
as soon as your page
gets loaded this particular script tag
would be executed right there and
then so it should work
it should reflect right away so it won't
wait for a click or anything
cool
we can make it
so it also happens on click
but as of now it would happen
automatically
as the page loads
okay so now let us
just say what is the parent element
of all of the li's here
anyone what is the parent
element for all of the li's here
remember all no matter
how many the children only
one parent can be there in this particular case
that parent is ul so
and do we have a
javascript element here
yes we have targeted
the ul lm before
only so i can say ul lm
dot
insert before
what is the new node
the new node is
seventh lm
and what are we inserting it before
what are we inserting this seventh lm
before
correct we are inserting it before eighth lm
and we have targeted it
here so which means
all i need to do is create it here
right
cool
what about if we have multiple
ul then how can we
check for parent in that case you need
to apply some sort of id or class
right
so that is the only way
cool
now
our code
looks somewhat fine
i am targeting the parent element
i am getting
all of the list from list i am getting
the eighth element i am creating
a new element li and in
that li i am setting the value as
7 and ultimately i am
on this particular parent lm
i am inserting seventh
element before eighth element
now the best thing about
these commands is that you could read it like a
sentence so
if i were to read this line i would say
on
ul lm insert before
seventh lm
eighth lm
so basically it is saying
for ul lm
insert seventh element
before eighth
element right so when i save this
and i go here it should probably
reflect and we have
7 here
so it works
basically
was everyone able
to follow this question
yes
tanu
sambit
sharanya
vineshwar upendra
shambhuraj
shashank
prajakta
pramod krishna
everyone was able to follow right
are you finding this question somewhat
interesting
yes
because next question onwards we are
upping the level a bit
what if we have to
search and insert
we are searching and inserting right
so right now
i knew for a fact that eighth element would be
existing here you can also
search also but that depends
how would you search and
what are you searching for so you need
to have some sort of clue there
based on that you can write
your logic
cool
cool then everyone
it's been almost
one hour would you like a break
should we move on to the next question
this is a somewhat
smaller only
it would take hardly five minutes for
to solve this
so let's do one thing we will solve this question
then we will take a quick break
cool
cool then let's
go ahead and solve this
question then
so
so the problem is fix
the mathematical problem using simply
js right
what is the problem
does it look wrong
yes it does and how
can we solve it
the ideal answer to
what is 2 plus 2 is it
22 yes or no
correct almost everyone
is saying 4 i think
my math is wrong
i have written 22 here so now that everyone
is saying 4 let's make it 4 but
how can we do so just using javascript
and nothing else
right how
can we do that
so first of all obviously i will have
to target
the p tag here
right
so let's target
let
para lm
is equal to document dot
get
not get
let's say query selector only
query selector
and let's make it p now
this is a test for you guys now tell me
would this target both
of the p's or would it target just
one p
both or one
we have used
query selector
correct correct so muneshwar
went a step further and provided
extra information it will also target
a first one this is what i was going to
ask next
in case one then which one
but ha so basically since we are using
query selector it will be targeting
the first element which matches this
condition in our case it's line
number 11 so which is
this particular
one right so let's fix
math on that one
and the simplest
way would be to say
para lm
dot
error text
is equal to
2 plus 2
is equal to 4
right let's go here
and change this to q3
and yes it is
working
cool
so we are able to target a first
element also and we are able to change
that also in case you wanted
to change for both that
anyway we will see an example of
this in upcoming question
but basically we will be using query selector
all and in the call will map
through each of the elements which
is there and i will be
applying the same logic
for each of those element but we
will see an example for this in upcoming
questions
cool then
now
just a second
it is
10.05 i think
it is 10.05 let's take a break for
5 minutes
we will
continue
at
10.10
cool
so we will be continuing at 10.10
meanwhile go for a walk
stretch your legs
and we will be solving the rest of
the questions starting 10.10
meanwhile if any one of you has
any doubts regarding
anything that we have discussed so far
now is the time
anything you all want to know
anything related to the question
anything related to any topic
that was not clear that we have covered so
far anything
related to any topic
that was not clear that we have covered so far
so is
everyone able to follow
so is everyone able to follow
Abhinav, Abhimanyu, Aima,
Ashish, Ashwini, Chandni
Dhanraj, Hevant,
Kishore, Krishna,
Munisura, Pradeep, Prajakta,
Pramod, Raja,
Rita, Sambhya, Sharanya,
Tanu, Tejal, Vipendra, Vigneshwar,
Priyanko, Rohit,
Shambhu, Raja, Shashank
Next question that we will be solving
is going to be a tricky one
and
we will see
but it is going to be a tricky one
yes that is correct
that is correct
if
we may
We also go
we also go take forever
we also take forever
go there for you
you
Yes, so this is one tiny thing that I used to do is so this is very very simple question
I'll be launching a pool and it is sort of like a game which no one is able to beat me so far
is you need to match there are only two options and you guys need to match some monkey it somehow
ends up with 50 50 percent for both of the options so let's see if so far no one has been able to
beat me at this as in king or no class whatsoever anyone has been able to score 50 50 landed the
poll result at 50 50 yet let's see if you guys are able to do that or not it's launching the poll
now
it's already 100% oh 71 29 I think again I'll be winning this one again no one would be able
to beat me and this particular thing once again 50 50 is hard now I told you it's a very tricky
thing at one point after scale you'd be you might be able to crack interviews but this question
no one's been able to beat me at this great cool let's begin with the second half of the lecture
now take now that everyone is back let me ask this again is these three questions clear to
everyone especially what all things we are learning what all tools we are learning to
solve these be it this query selector method like get element by ID query selector query
selector all get element by class name or beat about events active and listener and all of those
things is everyone able to follow for these yes I'm just an FYI in case you have any doubts
related to any of these things feel free to ask now with no doubt so far let's move on to the
big boss question like it's a one of the big question here so let's move on question four
okay that's a big one as I could see let me open the question here directly first okay so there
are a number of boxes here fine and okay let's see what the question is write a script which
fetches the data color attribute of the card on double click on them and attaches the fresh
glass to that card also change the data color attribute to used okay so you get right what
needs to be happened here cool to get so what needs to be happen here is we have the style
sheet already present with us right as you could see there is body blue green red card so we
have three such classes also present here blue green and red so what they're asking is key on
any of these square if I were to double click right if I were to double click I somehow need
to fetch the color on them I like in this particular case for the first card it is blue so I need to
fetch this blue and put it here right and change this blue to used when I do this you would see
it is not turned blue right same thing if I target this this one is red I need to copy this go here
paste red and change this red to used key as in case someone has already clicked on it so this
is what that has to be done right here so cool let's try and solve this so before we proceed is
clear is the end goal clear to everyone what has to be done yes take it so let's get coding for
this so what should be a first step somehow I need to attach an event listener on all of these
elements from what I can think right here I need to attach an event listener in that event listener
callback I'll be writing this logic key ticket if anyone were to double click on it then launch
this thing right basically launch this particular function in that function I somehow need to fetch
the value from this particular attribute and get it here right so there is something called get
attribute and set attribute that we have to learn for this right let me mention it here there is
get attribute and there is set attribute right these two get attribute is somewhat simple this
method returns the value of the elements attribute in our case the attribute that
we are targeting is data color so using this get attribute method I'll be somehow fetching the
value of that data and set attribute because after changing the color putting the color here in
classes I need to change this to used right so that can be done that can be done using set
attribute right it basically sets the new value of the elements attribute in our case
what is the new value that we are looking at correct the new value that we are looking at
is used yes okay so let's get rolling we need now I know the new thing that I have to do here
is use get attribute and set attribute right so let's get started so what should be my first
step any idea I say fire away on double click because I want my callback to be executed whenever
someone double clicks on something so I will listen to double click off card class because
I see card class is common across all right so I what I could have done I could have targeted
body and inside of this body I could have simply passed all of the elements inside of it but I
think it would be much simpler because all of them has card elements sorry card class so I can
simply use query selector all in this particular case right I can use query selector all and
and am I audible
cool cool cool so I could use query selector all and I can get all of these elements T now after
using query selector all I am putting a function on double click right so there must be an event
for double click event double click JavaScript in these case you don't need to remember anything
right so you can mostly rely on Google for these right okay so this event name is double click
D V L C L I C K so the normal click was simple click in here if I if I'm listening to a double
click so that is this one so whenever a double click happens in that case I have to do something
here right so I am I will be listening to double click on this what would be the next step I need
to somehow fetch the data color this could be done using get attribute right third would be
at the first attribute value as class right and after that I need to change data color to
used right and this would be done using set attribute is the plan clear to everyone that
what we what we will be doing to solve this particular problem we'll be listening to the
fire we'll be applying a double click we'll be listening to the double click event and in
the callback I'll be doing these three things I'll be fetching the data color using get attribute
I'll be taking the first value and put it in X class and as third point I'll take said attribute
and set this particular value data color of that particular thing that was double click to used
right I think it would work I think it would work right let's give this a try so first thing
first I need to attach an event listener to all of them right so let me target const cards is
equal to document dot query selector all help me with the query what should I write the query
selector value I'm targeting all the card using card class so how should I target what what we
should be writing here correct some would you you need to add dot also because this is query
selector on it does not know whether you're talking about ID or class or what so which means
you also need to add a dot so correct everyone I need to do dot card now if I were to console
dot log cards you would see I'm getting a list right I'm getting a list and it has all of these
cards right now all I have to do now is loop right all I have to do is loop so let's say for simple
let I is equal to zero I is less than cards dot length as you could see it also gives me the length
property at the end as well it is 10 right so this value would be there and I can do I plus plus
and now tell me I can do const current card is equal to cards I and in that current card dot add
event listener what event are we listening to what event are we listening to correct correct
Shambhuja Pramod we are listening to DBL click right and now let me console here first keep
whether it is working hello let's see I'm going to single click on it here first nothing gets
logged here now I'm going to double click on it see it's working double click let me also
add double click and index hello from index I so now I would also be knowing the index that
we are clicking so do you know which card this is what is the index of this card yes or no I
can tell this no no it's not zero how can this be zero there are so many above it right so randomly
what do you think is the index of this card do we know correct you won't you can't tell
but I can because I have written the JavaScript for it which will give me the index on double
click so all I have to do is double click and I get five so this is on index five what about
this one seven nine all of this is happening on double click not on single click right so now
are you guys able to somehow make an image key how those Rockstar developers that you are
thinking these are the basic concept that everyone follows right they don't change for everyone
better you are sitting at company a or company B this logic this learning these fundamentals
are same for all of them right all of them no key or double click this is how you will fire an event
right cool so this is all your firing element ticket so now my first task is done now the second
task is to get a data color using get attribute right let's do that how do you suggest we get
the value first of all we need to get an event here because we are listening to a certain event
it will give us the data about that element also right correct so here if I were to say let's say
on story console dot log event I'm getting this thing in here I have target in this target I have
the card which I want to make changes to right so what if I want to target event dot target right
see I'm getting green this one I'm getting blue this one I'm getting blue this one also
I'm getting blue this one I'm getting green right so so far so good right now how can I access a
certain value inside of this right I want to get a attribute on this particular thing so if I were
to expand this go to target you see we have so many things here and in here we
somewhere in here that particular method would be present that we are looking for see data
color and to access this data color get attribute method is present somewhere in here so let's
try and access it right let's say const class to be added is equal to event dot
target dot get attribute data color right this is the name of the attribute
you're targeting right now let me try console it and see if you are able to get it class to
see we're getting green blue blue red yes so we are able to get the class also so which
means this part is also done what is the next step I somehow need to take this class to be
added and include it here in class right correct so there is something called class list that is
present on each of these things suppose if I were to open this go to target right here there would
be something called class list somewhere classless see you have a class with present where it says
it only has one card class right so which means key in here you have certain methods which are
available right on this class list I can add contain entries for each to all of these things
so what I want to do do we want to remove anything from here yes or no correct no we
don't want to remove anything from here the point says add the fetched attribute value to the class
the we are able to fetch attribute here to add it I can simply use this add method right which
is present on class list which is present on the target element right so what I can say here is
simply it is as simple as invoking a method right so what I can say I can say even dot target dot
class list dot add what are we adding class to be added right let's save this finger crossed if
it works let's see it's not working why are we missing something here event or target let's
see if we are we are getting the values or not right let's start there okay my bad I think it
added oh yes it added we had hard-coded it here I've added a string here so I need the
value not the class we saw no changes here why how we are getting the path as in for what path
okay meanwhile can anyone tell me what what did we do wrong why even though class to be added
was written here but still no change was observed here any idea what could be the reason the last
which you written this one okay just give me a minute I'll get to it I've been up firstly how
about this you tell me why does this not work okay class to be added and a class was added here
but we don't see any difference here that is fine that is fine it was hard-coded but why don't we
see any difference here and there's a very simple reason for this like very simple reason
key why don't we see any difference even after a new class was added
correct correct so this is a very typical thing you see thing that I've done there is no class
written here right we have only classes present here for blue green and red so even though this
thing was added here class to be added we didn't see any differences so which is why I just removed
that thing here and now yes so it's working everyone which is interesting as you could see
this one is blue on clicking with this this would turn blue see we are legit adding interactivity
to our live website if that's not interesting that is like that should that should be like
unica moments for everyone right okay now you are asking something right can you show once I forget
where you get you are getting the path the last which you had written I think you're talking
about this path right class list add all of these things right okay I have unmuted you
yeah hi Sasha can you able to hear me yes yes loud and clear last line of code event dot target
dot class list dot add like this line you have taken from some classes right so we are from
where you are accessing their that path I just want to see once so let me go through it I'm
meeting you now right yeah cool so that's a good question let's go through it once again I'll be
logging it the event here and sold out log and this particular event will only be fired when I
double click on it right so let's see I say double click on this one I get an event in this event it
mentions key on what was the target what was the target that it received so this event is something
that we are receiving right this is the event on double click on some element right in this
particular case it's this element here if you were to go to target this target basically points to
this element in down right if I were to click here I think see it takes me back here so inside
of event dot target I've now expanded the target also you know I can scroll down scroll down scroll
down or no matter what classes are there all of those classes will be present inside of this value
class list no I'm not sure key whether uh has hasn't covered prototype with chaining with you
a prototype inheritance
yes he has right great great great so this would be much easier for you to understand now
key now see there is this class list but do you see any functions here even though I written
class list dot add but I don't see any function on this particular classes right so which means
key it is present here in its prototype right I can go to prototype and you can see all of
these methods are present here there is entries which will probably list all of these elements
there is for each it is like a iterable it will go through all of these one by one there is replace
remove keys items and the one that we are using which is add right and this is all I'm getting
to the add method so help me with the path event dot target dot class list dot add and that is all
I'm getting to this thing right so this is what I meant key this event is is such a enriching data
about what just happened then you can just play around with so many things here
right all of these have so many methods inside of it that you could play around with those
and get to the expected result that you want are we going to cover all tasks no we are not going
to cover all tasks we will be going through some of the tasks which would help in our use case
so which is why I say key you need to do a lot of self-study here right and to be honest if you if
I tell you about from my experience day-to-day work I have hardly used 80 percent of these things so
how many of you have heard about Pareto's principle there is something called Pareto
principle how many you
principle
that comes from experience now I have read it I'm correct Nishora so Pareto's principle this
is an interesting thing for each one of you like this is like a a guidebook for me especially when
I'm learning new things so this has helped me a lot so Pareto's principle is basically a 80-20 rule
so suppose say JavaScript is this big right there is HTML there is DOM there is a
JavaScript engine callback queue promises so many things are there right Pareto principle is very
simple it says key there is 20 percent of it that you will be using 20 percent and this is
80 percent right so this 20 percent of the things you will be using 80 percent of the time and this
80 percent of the things you will be using 20 percent of the time so in simple words basically
you should be targeting whenever you're learning new things you should be targeting to learn these
things because in your day-to-day job only 20 percent of the things of any new language you'll
be using 80 percent of the times think of it like this in dictionary you have so many words right
so many words are there but have you ever wondered key I hardly know any word from dictionary will
have not all of them but still I'm able to live through my life right because you as per Pareto's
principle you know 20 percent of the words which you are using 80 percent of the time so which is
why you are not blocked anywhere right so to get back to Abhinav's question how how am I going to
cover are we going to cover all the tags no what we are expiring to cover here is these 20 percent
of the topics which will be used 80 percent of the times and for these 80 percent of the topics
is something that you will have to cover on your own and we are here to assist you on that
does that make sense
no yes too much gap too much helping here
no
yes you can get all of these in w3 school
cool let's get back to the question now I hope that answered your question though Abhinav right
okay great great great
cool then so now we fetch the value as a class and this thing is also done the only thing left
is change the data color attribute right because we have to mark it as done
to mark it as done we have to do something like earlier we were doing get attribute this time
we'll have to do set attribute instead of get we have to do set what we are setting we are setting
data color we are setting data color to what we are setting data color to used
right and see that's it and we are good now let me reduce the size
okay as you could see now what I am going to do or take let's say let's pick this one
okay the color is right focus on this one this red will be shifted here
and this red would be turned to used
okay so this is the finished result yes
it's working right
and all of this is happening on double click
so I hope you all find it interesting well up these are the building blocks these are the
building these only are the building blocks and these things compound so these knowledge
especially these compound now that you have seen me using get attribute in set
attribute you are more or less comfortable now whenever in future
someone says to me how can I access this value here you know what to do right
likewise everyone this is the building block and now you know the way so let's
solve another question now yes let's move on to the new question yes no or is
there anyone who has any doubt regarding this question all good let's move on to
the fifth question now right this is the interesting one it says he jailed the
mouse okay question you are given an empty cell right let me open the
question first let's go to question five we are given an empty cell here we are
given an empty cell here write a script that whenever the mouse enters the mouse
is this mouse this mouse my computer mouse right so whenever the mouse
enters the cell jail should be drawn over it and it should be removed once it
leaves right there's a hint given also use the background image to set jail and
we have an image here right so the idea is here I should be able to wherever my
mouse enters this block there should this image should be loaded inside or
here right so sounds like an interesting problem to mouse to jail a mouse right
so let's give this a thing a try so let's go to question five what would be
my strategy let's talk about it so we basically need to have first of all we
need to target this element right target cell LM right this is the first thing it
would be probably easy for us to target we can use query selector or get element
by class name so the first one is somewhat easy then second is we need to
attach two event listener here what I am thinking one would be for mouse entered
and one would be for mouse left so can any one of you Google and let me know
what would be the event what would what would be the event that we should put in
add event listener like up until now we were putting DBL click or click for this
one mouse enter and mouse leave mouse left something so what event would be
there mouse mouse over mouse out mouse left so anyone help me with the what
should be the event that we are listening to right so we could probably
have one event listener for mouse enter and one event listener for mouse leave
is the strategy clear okay Muneeswara says we can use on mouse over because we
are using add event listener so we can drop the on we can just use mouse over
okay and what about mouse out correct oh there's a event called mouse out also so
we are using correct we will be using mouse over and mouse out so let's get
coding let's get coding so let's get done with the easiest part first let cell
is equal to equal to document dot query selector and what we are selecting for
cell right now in here I need to have two functions so cell dot document no
sorry cell dot add event listener what event listeners are we listening to
mouse over and mouse out okay let me mention it here mouse over and let's
have a callback here that we will write the function in some time and this one
would be mouse out okay to keep the code clean let's create a function outside on
mouse enter caused on mouse left tick I can paste it here and I can paste this
one here so this is done so on mouse enter I'll write a logic here I'll be
getting the event here so now what should we do on enter we should load
this particular image in the background image right so let's do how do you
likewise we were adding class list right corn sorry console dot log event so
let's see if it works I'll be entering mouse I'm getting an event I can go to
target there must be something called
there must be something called style in here style so no matter what CSS
property you may have heard of all of that gets eventually applied to this
right border top right radius true false all of the values that you possibly know
of thesis value gets eventually applied in here it's interesting right so which
means key you can change the styling also you can add classes you can add
values you can change values you can also add certain styles also in our case
the property that we are looking to change is the background image so there
must be a background image here somewhere this one okay so how do I
access this event target style dot background image there must be some
right so let's get started
actually we don't need event only in that cell element we had already
target here right so I can simply say cell
I can simply say cell dot style dot background image is equal to how do we
write the background image value we add the URL and in that URL I mention the
value in our case it is jail dash bars dot PNG right and what I could also say
is background dot background size is equal to cover cool let's see if it
works see it's working great right is everyone able to follow yes
great great great now we also have to remove it I think remove it removing it
is the easiest part so for remove it we know the basic value for background
image but the default value is empty string so I can just do it like this so
on mouse enter on mouse over this function would be called where we are
doing these two things on mouse left I'm simply doing this so which means key my
mouse would be trapped so now it's time to test
correct they could have also used hover I think in case my mouse is hovering over
it then show this as soon as my mouse is not hovering over it remove it so there
are multiple ways of solving this problem I used a long way because I
wanted to show key how multiple event listeners can be attached to a single
element but I hope it makes sense to everyone right yes right so this is also
done and this is also done great
cool so now let's get started with the sixth problem should I solve this
problem or you guys want to try it yourself this is an interesting one I
think okay got it so the problem statement for this one is key all of
these movies have a category present I think you should you should be able to
solve it right all of these things have a category present and when I say let's
say filter when I say romance you somehow need to filter all of the movies
here which meets the criteria for romance meets the criteria for comedy
meets the criteria for action so accordingly you need to filter all of
these and when I say none when I say none you need to bring back all of the
movies why target is not needed there just a second because we already have
the element in place right event or target is something which is present on
event right here to my element is already present if I were to use the
event which which I didn't when he saw right in that case I need to write it
like this event or target but because event or target would eventually point
to this only which I was able to pinpoint so which is why I didn't need
the event or target right because I didn't use event only I directly targeted
this particular element cool so for this one should I do it again I'll solve this
one you can solve the next one I'll solve this question six and then we can
call it a day well sounds like a plan yes let me solve question six then we
can start with a doubt-solving session let's get started
okay so do I worry about the classes no take it on click of all of these things
somehow I need to listen to first of all to the select element keep what is the
active value here right so active value needs to be selected first of all then
what I can say key whenever any change happens here any change happens I need
to react to it so one event listener that we had seen event JavaScript one
event listener that we I saw here is on change right and HTML element has been
changed right so in our case whenever this is changed from romance to action
action to comedy none basically this HTML element is changing so that is the
event listener that I will be listening to then I will simply be first of all
targeting all of the P element I would say then what I could simply say key by
if it is none do something if it is not none then I need to somehow get the
category key suppose this is romance right so I need to get a category of all
of these things and simply map over it key if your category is romance then you
will be visible in case it is not then you will not be visible and the
attribute that we will be playing around with for this could be display none how
does display none work suppose so here I'll just say display none see it is
gone so interesting thing about display none suppose I have this div right and I
say display none if you see here it is still on the dom but it is not visible
to everyone right so that's all you play around with display none so display none
it will be removed if I say display block it will be brought back there are
multiple values also inline block inline flex and all but I remember key this
must have been covered in one of the CSS classes because I've also covered this
in my batch right so we have a plan we have a strategy in place key my event
listener will be placed on here post that if any change happens I'll be seeing
the active value in case it is romance I need to access all of the divs all of
the divs with the class movies and I can say key if the category is action or
if the category matches the selection here then display would be blocked
otherwise display would be none right it's a strategy clear to everyone what
what strategy we will be pursuing yes is it clear yes Abhinavavimanyu
Aditya I am Ashish Chandni Dhanraj Kishore Heman Krishna Muniswara Pramod
Prajakta Pradeep Sambit Tanu Tejas Raja Ramesh Sita Vigneshwar Shashank yes great
great great ticket now I have my strategy so let's get coding by I hope
the pace and all is okay everyone is able to follow in case there is any doubt
feel free to ask if not feel free to stay back in the doubt solving session to
resolve your doubts right but we are learning a lot of new things today if
you think about it we just started with a simple hello question but now we are
this is like a actual full-fledged application problem to apply filter we
will be solving this so it's interesting that so far we have covered in last two
hours right if you can question is simple make the filter work so let's get
started first thing first I need to target the element so let's say const
filter lm is equal to document dot query selector right what how do I select this
okay we can this is the only selector so I can simply write select element so it
would pick the select element okay I can say filter lm dot add event listener
what event are we listening to change on change I will be getting a call back I
need to get the event here because I want to get the value also and I can be
logging event dot target dot value let's see if it works let's go to console
clear it changes to action they're getting action here changes to comedy
comedy romance so now I'm able to access all of the all of the available options
with me now all I have to do now is apply filter when I say filter I simply
have to based on the selected option pass through all of these lists and tell
he whether the data category whether the data category is comedy romance whether
it matches this condition or not yes so can anyone help me remember how will I
access us this particular attribute there is a method if I remember correctly
what was the method name we learned it in one of the questions earlier what is
the method name that we could use to access the attribute value he correct
correct it is get attribute correct correct promote also yes Munishwara
correct so let's get beginning
so let's say I want to add the filter value at my disposal so I don't have to
write event dot target dot value every time even dot target dot value and let's
say all tickets is equal to document dot query selector all p
ticket ticket now all we have to do is if filter value is equal to none in that
case what we have to do is basically I'm going to loop through the entire thing
and say let I is equal to zero I is less than all tickets dot then I plus plus
then I can say all tickets dot sorry all tickets me us IK parent element dot style
dot display is equal to lock what just happened if the filter value is none for
this as you could see I'm targeting the P element I'm targeting this particular
element not this element so I'm saying key for this particular element is
cap parent you access the parent element using this particular thing parent
element if I were to log also for this P tag you would find console dot log all
tickets see all tickets here somewhere in here parent element Namsevi something
would exist and that talks about this one parent element right so if I were to
extend extend this you would see again the whole thing started at the very top
we have access key for regarding this P tag right now we are the same for div
here right so you can access parent element also using this which is great
so what I was doing key in case the value is none I'm saying go through the
all of the list and through that list get to the parent element go to style and
set the display to block remember how we were accessing style here exactly like
this we are accessing style here also right
but what if it is not none in case it is not none then else else again we'll have
like this and what we have to do is all tickets all we have to do is if what
should be the data what should be the condition here basically the condition
is key if the data category matches filter value in that case set their
display to block otherwise set it to none so let's write it all tickets may
us I can you a dot get attribute what attribute are we looking for is sir data
dash category if data category is not equal to filter value in that case I'll
make it copy this paste it here and say no right else block cool does it make
sense what we are doing here let's see if it works first this is romance let me
say romance tea it works now we only have romance here let's change this to
comedy we have only eight and nine had comedy action we have these many
actions and if I were to say none all tenor back so it is working yes explain
once the logic yes so the logic was simple first thing I did I put an event
listener on change of this particular box right I said key by first or first of
all targeted to select element I read a event listener key change so every time
anything changes open it that's what I'm doing so every time anything changes I
get an event right and in that particular event I am passing a call back
which which will be getting that event and in that using that event first of
all I pick out the value give me this thing change to what right right now it
is none if change to romance right so which means key event or target dot
value is going to be romance here so romance is going to be stored in filter
value then what I did was as you could see there is a div there is such three
there is p tag my data category is present in p tag so what I did was key I
asked all of the p tags back all of the tickets query selector all p so far so
good here we can use callback function like that like what well so far we've
been using callback function like this only right
so we have all of the p tags here I'm not sure what's that let's stay back at
the inside of the loop no callback function is not inside of the loop
right callback function the loop is inside of the callback function not the
other way around cool then so we have this particular callback function here
we are accepting the event we got the value where this select value changed to
right in my case it changed to whatever value like in this particular case it
changed to romance so filter value is romance I targeted all of the p tags and
I simply simple logic now we're down to this part right if the filter value is
none if the filter value is none just go through all of the p tags go through
all of the p tags and make sure key all of the tickets that I got parent
element so basically we are saying go to let's say this particular p tag go to
its parent and set that style dot display to block and remember we what we
learn if I set a display to none it will be invisible if I set it to block it
will be visible so big which is why I simply said keep go through all of the
elements p tags go to their parent and in for that parent set it to block so
which is why they are visible when I say none everything is visible is it clear so
far the dry run part open the bin of emma it's clear right everyone able to
follow cheetah muniswara some bit promote great cricket ticket so now
coming to the latter part else in is in case it is not none so which means the
actual filter has to be applied so there needs to be another logic to check with
you whether the category matches the filter value or not yes or no so which
is why inside of it I am running another loop and in that loop it is exactly the
same as this loop but instead of setting all of the elements as block now I put a
condition here key if for that particular element get the attribute
data category data category attribute right and if is and if this matches the
filter value if this sorry if it does not matches the filter value then set
it to none and in case it does then set it to block right and it seems to be
working right
cool ticket so before ticket so so that's all I had planned for today's
lecture in next lecture we will be covering a lot of for dom things will be
will try to cover a couple of for machine coding problems as one doubt why
two blocks but if you could simplify the logic if you can find a better way then
yes you can simplify a logic this is the way I was thinking key if it is none
then set everything to block if it is not none so which means key I need to
apply some logic so I accepted like this so this is like a logic thing only
Abhinav polymorphism multiple ways of doing the same thing right I could I've
done it in this way maybe you can come up with a better approach to solving
this right so it is just about shifting lines here and there
cool yeah so in upcoming lecture obviously will be deep diving into more
such problems and more such things right like this so with that I hope you guys
enjoyed the lecture today and the pace and all was okay right I was not
rushing too much the other company no plan to nearer yes no yes no
great class looking forward thank you thank you Muneeswara ticket now that
being said any doubts whatsoever regarding anything now is your chance
to ask clarify brainstorm let's talk so any doubts anyone stay back in case you
don't have any doubts thank you thank you for attending the lecture and please
go through the recording and try to complete the assignment questions which
are very important obviously and I'll be pushing this code and I'll be adding a
couple more problems we haven't sought question number seven maybe that is
something that you can try on your own and in case you get stuck feel free to
reach on on the whatsapp group and we'll try to solve the question together right
so we'll do all of those things but for that obviously you guys also need to
take initiatives you guys also need to be involved so talking about being
involved any doubts regarding anything that we have covered in today's class
please share github link I'll be pushing this in the same link as Uttam was
pushing into so you'll find it in class 11 I'll do that in some time cool any
doubts any doubts anyone understanding concepts or code part is a bit
confusing any suggestion to overcome that as from non-tech no worries so
there's only one solution to all such things that is practice if you are able
to understand concept which as you mentioned you are able to understand
concept so it is just about practice at this part you already understand key why
we are doing certain things so as soon as you try your hands a couple of these
problems maybe what you could do you can remove all of the code that I have
written in today's class and you could try solving those problems on your own
obviously you you might find yourself stuck at certain points at that point
you could you know refer the answer that we have discussed in class right so that
way through practice you can somehow fortify your concepts right and once you
are able to because believe me from what coding is the easiest part
understanding concepts is the difficult part why you are doing certain things
why a is better than B or why B is better than A if you're able to tell
that then huh again same same upendra key if you are able to understand then
the coding is a lot easier today I feel interesting after nine classes of
full-style developer yes I'll be IK key classes or interesting whenever you are
so stay tuned right Pramod and upendra feel free to try this question I highly
highly recommend try these questions on your own try to solve them on your own
right if you feel stuck refer the question ripple the answer it's better
you feel stuck now then five months six months down the line at your actual job
right so please do that any doubts anyone any doubts anything you want me
to discuss again today and any part of the today's lecture that was not clear
anything that you want me to do no yes
cool then I guess there are no doubts so thanks thanks good night so what I'm
going to do now I'll close the class I'll upload the notes I'll push the code
I'll update the same on the whatsapp group and now post that it's on you guys
to go through the recording go through the assignment questions and in case you
get stuck then clarify your doubts on the whatsapp group right once you start
clarifying start discussing problem do all of those things and I will be active
on the whatsapp group answering all of your queries in case you don't want to
ask here right now right so with that good night good night I hope you guys
enjoyed the lecture and that's all that's all folks from my side right good
night it was super nice interacting with all of you and I'll see you guys soon on
30th 30th 30th right bye
you